There's some beautiful work around portraiture that you do with elders in the community too.
If you could talk just a little very briefly about the role of portraiture with first language speakers
in your native elders in the community.
Yeah, it just, it became, you know, something that I wanted people to see beauty within that's not,
you know, not the common beauty. What's what's a native beauty?
And that stems from what's beautiful around you, you know, to people in our community are beautiful,
our place around it and it stems from our grandma and like the last year of her life,
went to council be honored to be a beloved woman she didn't have to care about, you know,
being honored, she didn't know what were the words she was going to do there for.
But she just simply said, you know, you're all beautiful people.
Stop arguing, stop looking so, so hateful, you know, be proud and that's the thing is like,
we live in a beautiful environment. If you just take a breath and look out in Cherokee,
you're just like, Hannah, I live somewhere so beautiful and it's an unfortunate moniker that we live
in a beautiful place with like ugly people and that's not to say they're not aesthetically attractive
or aesthetically pleasing. It means that their spirit, their being is ugly and if we take a step back
and review those of our, you know, past and just really looking to that and looking at nature is like,
you know, sass of grass is a beautiful plant but it has beauty and aesthetic, it's not an aesthetically
beautiful plant but the intricacies of what it does for us as a people is beautiful. Same with the
basket maker or you know, you know, potter, you know, they might not be all glassy and shine,
shiny like, you know, stuff you might get in other stores but you know, that's beauty and the
fact that it was crafted by hands and I always refer back to Tom Bell saying of the word for
for making in Cherokee means to mend. It doesn't mean to create, you don't say you're creating a basket
is saying you're making really meaning a basket because these materials were given by our creator,
wasn't made by us. We're just meaning what's already there. Same with our medicine, same with our
plants, our animals, like they're all there for mutual benefit. How do we mutually do that? And how
do we, how do we show our appreciation and love is to re-evision that beauty in ways that isn't
aesthetics, what it really is, what really does, what does really feel that heart and so a series
that I've been doing for for families and for my family is just like, here's your ancestors,
here's where you come from, here's your lineage, go and look at them because it's the beauty that's
within them, is it within you, you carry beauty, you carry things, these things are transcendent
beyond what we are as a people, you know, we don't worry about this life or afterlife, we worry
about the existence and the continuance of our of our future generations and it's not seven generations,
we worry about like right now, how do we make sure we instill those things in those,
in those people that we have and how we create that appreciation for it, minds through art,
minds through storytelling, minds through whatever I can do to show that we need proper representation
and that's why I argue that those that might have a disconnection with the community but want
that space need to understand there are people that have to have space to properly introduce
their own families to what it is and so when they're not giving those opportunities,
it's like us being disconnected from that future generation and so that's why I was
telling people to hold off, you don't really know who your people are, or hold off before you
don't really know this place because there's a lot that goes on here, there's a lot of bad and
ugly that you might not see in between, you know, it's always really between the line, you know,
there's some ugly things that constantly go on, there's other things that about me, about my
practice about who I am but in the day I know I come from strong people and I have a strong understanding
and that I will not be a silent person when it comes to like empowering those voices that might not
have no the ability right now and it's just kind of where we go, it's kind of what we have to do
and to really understand that because those that speak without that connection, those that speak
without that understanding are hurting those that really do and we're tired of being silent
because our story isn't the saddest or our stories and the clickbait you want but it's true stories,
it's true histories and so when I do these drawings of my people of my grandma I'm just saying
hey she was a beautiful person she still is I'm called upon her when I need help when I need
protections and she'll do it she'll be there but I have to respect that she's doing other things
for other people as well and other areas that I'm never I'm not fully aware of at this point but
you know I hope people grasp that they grasp and truly understand that
a lot of people aren't here for enjoyment for exploitation we're here to be heard we're here to be
respected you know we're here to be seen truly seen I like making people nervous because this is
what they did and you know our grandmother grandma's grandmother she was removed from the Blue
Ridge Parkway at a young age because of relocation she was lameness luckily another tribal member
looked over them gave them land so it wasn't for that tribal member you know I would have been on
a lameness a lameless Cherokee my family my whole family would not have would have had land to
to see to anybody in the family and this is the Sequoia side and so thinking of that and then thinking
about you know all this is that's being populated by tourists and and roads and ecotourism I still
have I don't really like it because it's like where is our appreciation and where is our understanding
that this isn't your place to be like these streams waterways these trails these are for our people
we we've been listed on this and you know these are the same things that we've always been a part of
one little antidote for my childhood is that some cops didn't like come up to big cook because it's
a considered rough place they would they would take their time which is very troublesome when you
need things there in an immediacy and that's my childhood and that people might discredit that saying
that was it truly we just we are always there but as in a day when there's a distress for people
that supposed to take to them how does that really serve in the community and I think we need to
really take a deeper deeper dive into community love and to me understanding so that no
we can utilize these resources properly and not just utilize them because we have money
you know we had we had ways of respecting each other and keeping order
but we compound that with a you know idea of you know a cop being your your savior you're
discreeting those in your community that are also your savers that your grandma is your uncle
of your people that truly do listen and understand you know the reason I'm so powerful is because
I had a four foot eleven grandma who spoke her mind and made sure that we were respected as an
entire community of Cherokee people and she didn't need to call the cops to do that she didn't
need to you know do anything she just had to you know have cousins of cops of course she could
cut a cousin but it wasn't for me I was just help her out with stuff it's good to talk and express
because like they we're women you know we don't call it a father town we call it mother town can do
it you know we don't call Cherokee Nation you know I could have been our brother band they're
sister tribe you know they're that matriarch so we didn't respect that and we lose that ego that
male mass toxic masculinity and this like allow our women the feminine energy to it to kind of
to kind of bring combat to the to the forefront we're gonna be healthy we're gonna be successful
but it's not until we allow that and we're just gonna have more infighting we're gonna have more
arguing you know we're gonna just you know there was no arguing in grandma's house because we
respected that matriarch but there's a lot arguing now so how do we get that same respect and allow
that respect for everybody that you know truly deserves it and I don't think just because you have
position of power means you have power I think you need to utilize it in a better way and at times
you and my dad carries that you know that that does matriarchal understanding and then my uncle and
law does that as well because they're raised by women and those women care those things and so
it's not to say our our men aren't you know aren't a bailout are able to do things and to respect
things I just think we just have to understand where that strength comes from and it comes
from that matriarch and I I'm really appreciative and I hope you know my children really respect and
understand those things too and value themselves you know I have one you have four kids and
three of them are girls and the last thing I would want them to be is through like they are
they owe somebody something of themselves I want them to you feel like you have all the power
and all the strength you have all the backing so these things help me express those things because
you know I love all my kids I love my family and I just want them to you know feel that
they're important and you know everybody's important but and again using spaces and places like
best to just bring home those points are very helpful and something I'm trying to do more of because
I think we we need to occupy these places that sometimes get discussed with people it might not
be the best yet